Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Events
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Events
1939-
The Museum of Modern Art, Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019-5497 Phone: (212) 708-9617 Fax: (212) 408-6385 Email: archives@moma.org
The Museum of Modern Art
Provenance
Sound recordings were made for the individual Museum department responsible for the event, namely the Departments of Architecture and Design, Education, Film, Painting and Sculpture, and Public Information. Before the Audio-Visual Archives was established in 1966, the Museum Library stored sound recordings as well as photographs and slides. In 1971, this material became part of the Department of Rights and Reproductions where it remained until 1980 when sound recordings were once again stored in the Library. The first 887 recordings of the collection were transferred from the Library to the Museum Archives in June 1990. Subsequent recordings were transferred to the Museum Archives from various departments, June 1990 to the present.
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Museum Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Architecture and Design.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Audio-Visual Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Education.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Film.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Painting and Sculpture.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Public Information.; International Council of The Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Junior Council.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.) -- Congresses.; Cineprobe.; New directors/new films.; Video viewpoints.; Symposia.; Interviews.; Lectures.; Speeches.
Access Restrictions
The records are open for research and contain few restricted materials.
Scope and Content Note
This Record Group contains recordings of events that either occurred at or are related to Museum of Modern Art activities. Types of events include interviews, lectures, speeches, symposia, panel discussions, and discussions between filmmakers and audience.
The first 887 sound recordings in the collection were produced from 1939 through 1988 and transferred to the Museum Archives in June 1990. The description of those recordings replicates an index card file created by previous custodians of the collection.
Recordings transferred to the archives after June 1990 and continuing to the present were cataloged as received. Included in this group are three tape recordings of the 1939 Museum opening, transferred to the Museum Archives in September 1990.
Types of recording media found in the collection include: 4 10" sound tape reels, 673 7" sound tape reels, 178 5" sound tape reels, 20 3" sound tape reels, 1 Cousino Echo-matic II self-threading tape cartridge, and 1 continuous loop tape. More recent media include standard audio cassettes and various digital recording formats.
Examples of program series represented by the recordings include The Related Arts of Today, Cineprobe, New Films/New Directors,What's Happening?,Requests from the Archives,Views on Art,Video Viewpoints,Looking at Film, and Italian Filmmakers. Sponsors include the National Endowment for the Arts, National Endowment for the Humanities, New York State Council on the Arts, Jerome Foundation, the Roy and Niuta Titus Fund; and the Junior Council, International Council, Department of Film, Department of Painting and Sculpture, and Department of Education of the Museum.
In 1978 a new program was started by Barbara London, a curator in the Department of Film, concerning artists and their recent media projects. Focusing on experimentation with form and content, the program features both emerging and recognized artists, who discuss their work with the audience. The programs are presented biweekly and explore filmmaking and videomaking, as well as Web-based, installation, and digital art practices. The program was titled Video Viewpoints until 2003 when its name was changed to MediaScope. These recordings have been aranged as a separate group under the heading Video Viewpoints.
Arrangement
Within the general sound recordings, recordings through 1997 are arranged chronologically. Each recording is identified by an inventory number that corresponds to a descriptive entry. Recording number 58.6 refers to the sixth event recorded in 1958. The descriptive entry includes such information as personality, title, date, place, series, participants, sponsor, exhibition, size of tape, speed of tape, length of tape, related material, summary, and donor. Original order has been maintained, therefore there are instances when tape recordings from a single year were inventoried out of sequence: for example, 72.13 occurred on March 17th, whereas 72.14 occurred on March 16th.
Sound recordings 71.30, 71.36, 71.38, 74.5, 74.7, and 74.12 in Series A are missing although original index cards for them exist. In addition, the descriptive index cards transferred to the Museum Archives in 1990 with the sound recordings indicated that there were "no corresponding tapes" for sound recordings 69.2, 69.32, and 69.37.
Beginning in January 1998, sound recordings are catalogued according to the date of accession by the Museum Archives, not, as was previously done, by date of event; i.e. tape 98.6 -- the sixth recording to enter the Museum Archives collection of sound recordings in the calendar year 1998. Sound recordings are arranged numerically by accession number. The decision to change the catalogue numbering system was made in order to maximize the efficiency of the transfer process.
Within the series devoted to Video Viewpoints, recordings are described in the order they were received. The same numbering system is used to identify recordings with "vv" as a prefix to indicate that they form part of the Video Viewpoints series.
A cassette player, a discman and a personal DVD player required to play these recordings are available at The Museum of Modern Art Archives. Equipment required for listening to the reel-to-reel tapes, 10" sound recordings, the Cousino Echomatic II self-threading tape cartridge, and the continuous tape loop is not available.
Related Collections at MoMA and Elsewhere
See also, Registrar exhibition files; transcripts of the Video Viewpoints series in the office of the Media Department; documentation in the Film Study Center; and records in the Museum Archives.
Container List
- General Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Activities, 1939-present
  - "Opening of The Museum of Modern Art", May 10, 1939; PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, Lowell Thomas, Edward Bruce, Edsel Ford, John Hay Whitney, Walt Disney (on the history of film), Dean Robert Hutchins, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt DATA: One 60-minute Standard Audio Cassette, duplicate is 90 minute cassette, third duplicate is DAT. SUMMARY: Addresses given on the occasion of the tenth anniversary of The Museum of Modern Art.: 39.1b, D39.1a/b, Please see Transcripts, Folder 1 TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 18, 1990; NOTE: One of two master cassettes taken from seven audio discs of the same title in the Museum's collection; duplicated by the Museum of Broadcasting, March 20, 1985. Duplicate was created on May 11, 1989. This sound recording was preserved in Fall 2006. In addition to the original and the two duplicate cassettes copies, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. A separate compact disc containing only President Franklin Delano Roosevelt's speech was also created. (Item 39.1a, 39.1D)
  - "Opening of The Museum of Modern Art", May 10, 1939; PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mayor Fiorello La Guardia, Lowell Thomas, Edward Bruce, Edsel Ford, John Hay Whitney, Walt Disney (on the history of film), Dean Robert Hutchins, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt DATA: One 60-minute Standard Audio Cassette, duplicate is 90 minute cassette, third duplicate is DAT. SUMMARY: Addresses given on the occasion of the tenth anniversary of The Museum of Modern Art. RELATED MATERIAL: 39.1a, D39.1a/b, Please see Transcripts, Folder 1 TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 18, 1990; NOTE: One of two master cassettes taken from seven audio discs of the same title in the Museum's collection; duplicated by the Museum of Broadcasting, March 20, 1985. Duplicate was created on May 11, 1989. This sound recording was preserved in Fall 2006. In addition to the original and the two duplicate cassettes copies, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. A separate compact disc containing only President Franklin Delano Roosevelt's speech was also created. (Item 39.1b, 39.1D)
  - "The Writer Looks At Painting", February 26, 1952 (?); NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; PERSONALITY: Janet Flanner Genet DATA: 5" reel (Item 52.1, 52.1D)
  - "Comparison of Advertising in the U.S. and Europe", October 27, 1952; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; SERIES: WNYC Art Festival PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Mildred Constantine; Panel Members: Leo Lionni, Will Burton DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Panel discussion (Item 52.2, 52.2D)
  - "U.S. Architecture Today", October 28, 1952; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; SERIES: WNYC Art Festival PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Philip Johnson; Henry-Russell Hitchcock, Arthur Drexler DATA: 7" reel (Item 52.3, 52.3D)
  - "The Fauves", October 29, 1952; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; SERIES: WNYC Art Festival PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Andrew C. Ritchie; Alfred H. Barr, Jr., James Thrall Soby DATA: 7" reel (Item 52.4, 52.4D)
  - "A New Century of Print Making", October, 1952; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; SERIES: WNYC Art Festival PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: William S. Lieberman; Grace Borgenicht (dealer), Maxil Ballinger (artist), Richard Hunt (collector and Junior Council) DATA: 7" reel (Item 52.5, 52.5D)
  - "Art for Adults & Children", October 30, 1952; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; SERIES: WNYC Art Festival PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Miss Nora Hecht (PAC); Miss Lily Fenichel (teacher of children), Mrs. Sophy P. Regensburg (adult student) DATA: 7" reel (Item 52.6, 52.6D)
  - "Art Under the Soviet and Nazi Dictatorships", December 10, 1952; (#1 of 4) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Alfred H. Barr, Jr. SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated talk by Alfred H. Barr, Jr. (Director of Museum Collections) RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.8, 52.9, 52.10; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.7, 52.7D)
  - "Art Under The Soviet and Nazi Dictatorships", December 10, 1952; (#2 of 4) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Alfred H. Barr, Jr. SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated talk by Alfred H. Barr, Jr. (Director of Museum Collections) RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.7, 52.9, 52.10; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.8, 52.8D)
  - "Art Under The Soviet and Nazi Dictatorships", December 10, 1952; (#3 of 4) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Alfred H. Barr, Jr. SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated talk by Alfred H. Barr, Jr. (Director of Museum Collections) RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.7, 52.8, 52.10; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.9, 52.9D)
  - "Art Under The Soviet and Nazi Dictatorships", December 10, 1952; (#4 of 4) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Alfred H. Barr, Jr. SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated talk by Alfred H. Barr, Jr. (Director of Museum Collections) RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.7, 52.8, 52.9; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.10, 52.10D)
  - "The Writer Looks at Painting", February 26, 1952; (#1 of 3) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Monroe Wheeler, Elmer Rice (playwright), Marianne Moore (poet), Kenneth Burke (philosopher), Janet Flanner (New Yorker), Glenway Wescott (author) SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.12, 52.13; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.11, 52.11D)
  - "The Writer Looks at Painting", February 26, 1952; (#2 of 3) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.11, 52.13; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.12, 52.12D)
  - "The Writer Looks at Painting", February 26, 1952; (#3 of 3) SERIES: The Related Arts of Today DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 52.11, 52.12; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 52.13, 52.13D)
  - "Art & Advertising: New Forms vs. Cliches", February 4, 1953; (#1 of 4) SERIES: Related Arts and Advertising PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Mildred Constantine; Speakers: Leo Lionni (Art Director,Fortune), Paul Smith (Art Director, Calking, Holders, McClintok & Smith), Alfred Auerbach, William H. Whyte (Fortune magazine Writer) SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 53.2, 53.3, 53.4; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.1, 53.1D)
  - "Art & Advertising: New Forms vs. Cliches", February 4, 1953; (#2 of 4) SERIES: Related Arts and Advertising PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Mildred Constantine; Speakers: Leo Lionni (Art Director,Fortune), Paul Smith (Art Director, Calking, Holders, McClintok & Smith), Alfred Auerbach, William H. Whyte (Fortune magazine Writer) SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 53.1, 53.3, 53.4; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.2, 53.2D)
  - "Art & Advertising: New Forms vs. Cliches", February 4, 1953; (#3 of 4) SERIES: Related Arts and Advertising PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Mildred Constantine; Speakers: Leo Lionni (Art Director,Fortune), Paul Smith (Art Director, Calking, Holders, McClintok & Smith), Alfred Auerbach, William H. Whyte (Fortune magazine Writer) SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 53.1, 53.2, 53.4; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.3, 53.3D)
  - "Art & Advertising: New Forms vs. Cliches", February 4, 1953; (#4 of 4) SERIES: Related Arts and Advertising PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Mildred Constantine; Speakers: Leo Lionni (Art Director,Fortune), Paul Smith (Art Director, Calking, Holders, McClintok & Smith), Alfred Auerbach, William H. Whyte (Fortune magazine Writer) SPONSOR: Junior Council DATA: 7" reel RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 53.1, 53.2, 53.3; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.4, 53.4D)
  - "Traditional Religion & Contemporary Art", April 8, 1953; (#1 of 2) PLACE: Museum Auditorium SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Edgar Wind SPONSOR: Junior Council EXHIBITION:Georges Rouault[MoMA Exh. #535, March 31-May 31, 1953] DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated address by Edgar Wind on the occasion of the Rouault Exhibition RELATED MATERIAL: Tape 53.6; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.5, 53.5D)
  - "Traditional Religion & Contemporary Art", April 8, 1953; (#2 of 2) PLACE: Museum Auditorium SERIES: The Related Arts of Today PARTICIPANTS: Edgar Wind SPONSOR: Junior Council EXHIBITION:Georges Rouault[MoMA Exh. #535, March 31-May 31, 1953] DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Illustrated address by Edgar Wind on the occasion of the Rouault Exhibition RELATED MATERIAL: Tape 53.5; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.6, 53.6D)
  - "The Museum of Modern Art Reopening", April 29, 1953; PERSONALITY: Frank Blair, Aline Saarinen PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art SERIES: "Sunday," NBC News Program PARTICIPANTS: Frank Blair, Aline Saarinen DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Tape for "Sunday," a NBC News Program; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.6a, 53.6aD)
  - "Young Poets", May 13, 1953; PLACE: Museum Auditorium PARTICIPANTS: Introduction: Marianne Moore and W.H. Auden DATA: 7" reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist. (Item 53.7, 53.7D)
  - "Lger lecture", November 18, 1953; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; PARTICIPANTS: James Johnson Sweeney EXHIBITION:Lger[MoMA Exh. #545, October 20, 1953-January 3, 1954] DATA: 7" reel; both sides (Item 53.8, 53.8D)
  - "Ancient Art of the Andes", February 24, 1954; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; (#1 of 2) PARTICIPANTS: Ren d'Harnoncourt (Director of The Museum of Modern Art) EXHIBITION:Ancient Arts of the Andes[MoMA Exh. #550, January 25-March 21, 1954] DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Talk by Ren d'Harnoncourt RELATED MATERIAL: 54.2; Please see Transcripts, Folder 2 (Item 54.1, 54.1D)
  - "Ancient Art of the Andes", February 24, 1954; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; (#2 of 2) PARTICIPANTS: Ren d'Harnoncourt (Director of The Museum of Modern Art) EXHIBITION:Ancient Arts of the Andes[MoMA Exh. #550, January 25-March 21, 1954] DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Talk by Ren d'Harnoncourt RELATED MATERIAL: 54.1; Please see Transcripts, Folder 2 (Item 54.2, 54.2D)
  - "President Eisenhower's Speech - 25th Anniversary," Original, October 19, 1954; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; DATA: 5" reel SUMMARY: [NOTE (6/26/90): Tape 54.3 needs to be spliced] RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes D54.3 (3 copies) (Item 54.3)
  - "25th Anniversary Ceremonies", October 19, 1954; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; (#1 of 3) DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Duplicate of tape 54.3 RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 54.3, D54.3 (#2 and #3)[NOTE (6/26/90): Tape 54.3 needs to be spliced] (Item D54.3)
  - "25th Anniversary Ceremonies", October 19, 1954; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2001 through a generous grant from the New York State Education Department and Library. In addition to the original, a 10.5 inch analog reel-to-reel archival master, a CD-R use copy and a CD-R back-up copy now exist.; (#2 of 3) SERIES: President Eisenhower's speech DATA: 7" reel SUMMARY: Duplicate of 54.3 RELATED MATERIAL: Tapes 54.3, D54.3 (#1 and #3)[NOTE (6/26/90): Tape 54.3 needs to be spliced] (Item D54.3)